
	morphic.js

	a lively Web-GUI
	inspired by Squeak

	written by Jens Mönig
	jens@moenig.org

	Copyright (C) 2012 by Jens Mönig

	this documentation last changed: September 13, 2012

	This file is part of Snap!. 

	Snap! is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as
	published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of
	the License, or (at your option) any later version.

	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	GNU Affero General Public License for more details.

	You should have received a copy of the GNU Affero General Public License
	along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.


	documentation contents
	----------------------
	I. inheritance hierarchy
	II. object definition toc
	III. yet to implement
	IV. open issues
	V. browser compatibility
	VI. the big picture
	VII. programming guide
		(1) setting up a web page
			(a) single world
			(b) multiple worlds
			(c) an application
		(2) manipulating morphs
		(3) events
			(a) mouse events
			(b) context menu
			(c) dragging
			(d) dropping
			(e) keyboard events
			(f) resize event
            (g) combined mouse-keyboard events
		(4) stepping
		(5) creating new kinds of morphs
		(6) development and user modes
		(7) turtle graphics
		(8) damage list housekeeping
		(9) minifying morphic.js
	VIII. acknowledgements
	IX. contributors


	I. hierarchy
	-------------
	the following tree lists all constructors hierarchically,
	indentation indicating inheritance. Refer to this list to get a
	contextual overview:

	Color
	Node
		Morph
			BlinkerMorph
				CursorMorph
			BouncerMorph*
			BoxMorph
				InspectorMorph
				MenuMorph
				MouseSensorMorph*
				SpeechBubbleMorph
			CircleBoxMorph
				SliderButtonMorph
				SliderMorph
			ColorPaletteMorph
				GrayPaletteMorph
			ColorPickerMorph
			FrameMorph
				ScrollFrameMorph
					ListMorph
				StringFieldMorph
				WorldMorph
			HandleMorph
			HandMorph
			PenMorph
			ShadowMorph
			StringMorph
			TextMorph
			TriggerMorph
				MenuItemMorph
	Point
	Rectangle


	II. toc
	-------
	the following list shows the order in which all constructors are
	defined. Use this list to locate code in this document:


	Global settings
	Global functions

	Color
	Point
	Rectangle
	Node
	Morph
	ShadowMorph
	HandleMorph
	PenMorph
	ColorPaletteMorph
	GrayPaletteMorph
	ColorPickerMorph
	BlinkerMorph
	CursorMorph
	BoxMorph
	SpeechBubbleMorph
	CircleBoxMorph
	SliderButtonMorph
	SliderMorph
	MouseSensorMorph*
	InspectorMorph
	MenuMorph
	StringMorph
	TextMorph
	TriggerMorph
	MenuItemMorph
	FrameMorph
	ScrollFrameMorph
	ListMorph
	StringFieldMorph
	BouncerMorph*
	HandMorph
	WorldMorph

	* included only for demo purposes


	III. yet to implement
	---------------------
	- keyboard support for scroll frames and lists


	IV. open issues
	----------------
	- blurry shadows don't work well in Chrome


	V. browser compatibility
	------------------------
	I have taken great care and considerable effort to make morphic.js
	runnable and appearing exactly the same on all current browsers
	available to me:

	- Firefox for Windows
	- Firefox for Mac
	- Chrome for Windows (blurry shadows have some issues)
	- Chrome for Mac
	- Safari for Windows
	- safari for Mac
	- Safari for iOS (mobile)
	- IE for Windows
	- Opera for Windows
	- Opera for Mac


	VI. the big picture
	-------------------
	Morphic.js is completely based on Canvas and JavaScript, it is just
	Morphic, nothing else. Morphic.js is very basic and covers only the
	bare essentials:

        * a stepping mechanism (a time-sharing multiplexer for lively
          user interaction ontop of a single OS/browser thread)
		* progressive display updates (only dirty rectangles are
          redrawn in each display cycle)
		* a tree structure
		* a single World per Canvas element (although you can have
          multiple worlds in multiple Canvas elements on the same web
          page)
		* a single Hand per World (but you can support multi-touch
          events)
		* a single text entry focus per World

	In its current state morphic.js doesn't support Transforms (you
	cannot rotate Morphs), but with PenMorph there already is a simple
	LOGO-like turtle that you can use to draw onto any Morph it is
	attached to. I'm planning to add special Morphs that support these
	operations later on, but not for every Morph in the system.
	Therefore these additions ("sprites" etc.) are likely to be part of
	other libraries ("microworld.js") in separate files.

	the purpose of morphic.js is to provide a malleable framework that
	will let me experiment with lively GUIs for my hobby horse, which
	is drag-and-drop, blocks based programming languages. Those things
	(BYOB4 - http://byob.berkeley.edu) will be written using morphic.js
	as a library.


	VII. programming guide
	----------------------
	Morphic.js provides a library for lively GUIs inside single HTML
	Canvas elements. Each such canvas element functions as a "world" in
	which other visible shapes ("morphs") can be positioned and
	manipulated, often directly and interactively by the user. Morphs
	are tree nodes and may contain any number of submorphs ("children").

	All things visible in a morphic World are morphs themselves, i.e.
	all text rendering, blinking cursors, entry fields, menus, buttons,
	sliders, windows and dialog boxes etc. are created with morphic.js
	rather than using HTML DOM elements, and as a consequence can be
	changed and adjusted by the programmer regardless of proprietary
	browser behavior.

	Each World has an - invisible - "Hand" resembling the mouse cursor
	(or the user's finger on touch screens) which handles mouse events,
	and may also have a keyboardReceiver to handle key events.

	The basic idea of Morphic is to continuously run display cycles and
	to incrementally update the screen by only redrawing those  World
	regions	which have been "dirtied" since the last redraw. Before
	each shape is processed for redisplay it gets the chance to perform
	a "step" procedure, thus allowing for an illusion of concurrency.


	(1) setting up a web page
	-------------------------
	Setting up a web page for Morphic always involves three steps:
	adding one or more Canvas elements, defining one or more worlds,
	initializing and starting the main loop.


	(a) single world
	-----------------
	Most commonly you will want your World to fill the browsers's whole
	client area. This default situation is easiest and most straight
	forward.

	example html file:

	<!DOCTYPE html>
	<html>
		<head>
			<title>Morphic!</title>
			<script type="text/javascript" src="morphic.js"></script>
			<script type="text/javascript">
				var world;

				window.onload = function () {
					world = new WorldMorph(
						document.getElementById('world'));
					setInterval(loop, 50);
				};

				function loop() {
					world.doOneCycle();
				}
			</script>
		</head>
		<body>
			<canvas id="world" tabindex="1" width="800" height="600">
				<p>Your browser doesn't support canvas.</p>
			</canvas>
		</body>
	</html>

	if you use ScrollFrames or otherwise plan to support mouse wheel
	scrolling events, you might also add the following inline-CSS
	attribute to the Canvas element:

		style="position: absolute;"

	which will prevent the World to be scrolled around instead of the
	elements inside of it in some browsers.


	(b) multiple worlds
	-------------------
	If you wish to create a web page with more than one world, make
	sure to prevent each world from auto-filling the whole page and
	include	it in the main loop. It's also a good idea to give each
	world its own tabindex:

	example html file:

	<!DOCTYPE html>
	<html>
		<head>
			<title>Morphic!</title>
			<script type="text/javascript" src="morphic.js"></script>
			<script type="text/javascript">
				var world1, world2;

				window.onload = function () {
					world1 = new WorldMorph(
						document.getElementById('world1'), false);
					world2 = new WorldMorph(
						document.getElementById('world2'), false);
					setInterval(loop, 50);
				};

				function loop() {
					world1.doOneCycle();
					world2.doOneCycle();
				}
			</script>
		</head>
		<body>
			<p>first world:</p>
			<canvas id="world1" tabindex="1" width="600" height="400">
				<p>Your browser doesn't support canvas.</p>
			</canvas>
			<p>second world:</p>
			<canvas id="world2" tabindex="2" width="400" height="600">
				<p>Your browser doesn't support canvas.</p>
			</canvas>
		</body>
	</html>


	(c) an application
	-------------------
	Of course, most of the time you don't want to just plain use the
	standard Morhic World "as is" out of the box, but write your own
	application (something like Scratch!) in it. For such an
	application you'll create your own morph prototypes, perhaps
	assemble your own "window frame" and bring it all to life in a
	customized World state. the following example creates a simple
	snake-like mouse drawing game.

	example html file:

	<!DOCTYPE html>
	<html>
		<head>
			<title>touch me!</title>
			<script type="text/javascript" src="morphic.js"></script>
			<script type="text/javascript">
				var worldCanvas, sensor;

				window.onload = function () {
					var x, y, w, h;

					worldCanvas = document.getElementById('world');
					world = new WorldMorph(worldCanvas);
					world.isDevMode = false;
					world.color = new Color();

					w = 100;
					h = 100;

					x = 0;
					y = 0;

					while ((y * h) < world.height()) {
						while ((x * w) < world.width()) {
							sensor = new MouseSensorMorph();
							sensor.setPosition(new Point(x * w, y * h));
							sensor.alpha = 0;
							sensor.setExtent(new Point(w, h));
							world.add(sensor);
							x += 1;
						}
						x = 0;
						y += 1;
					}
					setInterval(loop, 50);
				};

				function loop() {
					world.doOneCycle();
				}
			</script>
		</head>
		<body bgcolor='black'>
			<canvas id="world" width="800" height="600">
				<p>Your browser doesn't support canvas.</p>
			</canvas>
		</body>
	</html>

	To get an idea how you can craft your own custom morph prototypes
	I've included two examples which should give you an idea how to add
	properties, override inherited methods and use the stepping
	mechanism for "livelyness":

		BouncerMorph
		MouseSensorMorph

	For the sake of sharing a single file I've included those examples
	in morphic.js itself. Usually you'll define your additions in a
	separate file and keep morphic.js untouched.


	(2) manipulating morphs
	-----------------------
	There are many methods to programmatically manipulate morphs. Among
	the most important and common ones among all morphs are the
	following nine:

	* hide()
	* show()

	* setPosition(aPoint)
	* setExtent(aPoint)
	* setColor(aColor)

	* add(submorph)			- attaches submorph ontop
	* addBack(submorph)		- attaches submorph underneath

	* fullCopy()			- duplication
	* destroy()				- deletion


	(3) events
	----------
	All user (and system) interaction is triggered by events, which are
	passed on from the root element - the World - to its submorphs. The
	World contains a list of system (browser) events it reacts to in its

		initEventListeners()

	method. Currently there are

		- mouse
        - drop
		- keyboard
		- (window) resize

	events.

	These system events are dispatched within the morphic World by the
	World's Hand and its keyboardReceiver (usually the active text
	cursor).


	(a) mouse events:
	-----------------
	The Hand dispatches the following mouse events to relevant morphs:

		mouseDownLeft
		mouseDownRight
		mouseClickLeft
		mouseClickRight
		mouseEnter
		mouseLeave
		mouseEnterDragging
		mouseLeaveDragging
		mouseMove
		mouseScroll

	If you wish your morph to react to any such event, simply add a
	method of the same name as the event, e.g:

		MyMorph.prototype.mouseMove = function(pos) {};

	The only optional parameter of such a method is a Point object
	indicating the current position of the Hand inside the World's
	coordinate system.

	Events may be "bubbled" up a morph's owner chain by calling

		this.escalateEvent(functionName, arg)

	in the event handler method's code.

	Likewise, removing the event handler method will render your morph
	passive to the event in question.


	(b) context menu:
	-----------------
	By default right-clicking (or single-finger tap-and-hold) on a morph
	also invokes its context menu (in addition to firing the
	mouseClickRight event). A morph's context menu can be customized by
	assigning a Menu instance to its

		customContextMenu

	property, or altogether suppressed by overriding its inherited

		contextMenu()

	method.


	(c) dragging:
	-------------
	Dragging a morph is initiated when the left mouse button is pressed,
	held and the mouse is moved.

	You can control whether a morph is draggable by setting its

		isDraggable

	property either to false or true. If a morph isn't draggable itself
	it will pass the pick-up request up its owner chain. This lets you
	create draggable composite morphs like Windows, DialogBoxes,
	Sliders etc.

	Sometimes it is desireable to make "template" shapes which cannot be
	moved themselves, but from which instead duplicates can be peeled
	off. This is especially useful for building blocks in construction
	kits, e.g. the MIT-Scratch palette. Morphic.js lets you control this
	functionality by setting the

		isTemplate

	property flag to true for any morph whose "isDraggable" property is
	turned off. When dragging such a Morph the hand will instead grab
	a duplicate of the template whose "isDraggable" flag is true and
	whose "isTemplate" flag is false, in other words: a non-template.

	Dragging is indicated by adding a drop shadow to the morph in hand.
	If a morph follows the hand without displaying a drop shadow it is
	merely being moved about without changing its parent (owner morph),
	e.g. when "dragging" a morph handle to resize its owner, or when
	"dragging" a slider button.

	Right before a morph is picked up its

		prepareToBeGrabbed(handMorph)

	method is invoked, if it is present. Immediately after the pick-up
	the former parent's

		reactToGrabOf(grabbedMorph)

	method is called, again only if it exists.

	Similar to events, these  methods are optional and don't exist by
	default. For a simple example of how they can be used to adjust
	scroll bars in a scroll frame please have a look at their
	implementation in FrameMorph.


	(d) dropping:
	-------------
	Dropping is triggered when the left mouse button is either pressed
	or released while the Hand is dragging a morph.

	Dropping a morph causes it to become embedded in a new owner morph.
	You can control this embedding behavior by setting the prospective
	drop target's

		acceptsDrops

	property to either true or false, or by overriding its inherited

		wantsDropOf(aMorph)

	method.

	Right after a morph has been dropped its

		justDropped(handMorph)

	method is called, and its new parent's

		reactToDropOf(droppedMorph, handMorph)

	method is invoked, again only if each method exists.

	Similar to events, these  methods are optional and by default are
	not present in morphs by default (watch out for inheritance,
	though!). For a simple example of how they can be used to adjust
	scroll bars in a scroll frame please have a look at their
	implementation in FrameMorph.

	Drops of image elements from outside the world canvas are dispatched as

		droppedImage(aCanvas, name)

	events to interested Morphs at the mouse pointer. If you want you Morph
	to e.g. import outside images you can add the droppedImage() method to
	it. The parameter passed to the event handles is a new offscreen
	canvas element representing a copy of the original image element which
	can be directly used, e.g. by assigning it to another Morph's image
	property.

	The same applies to drops of audio or text files from outside the world
	canvas.

	Those are dispatched as
    
		droppedAudio(anAudio, name)
		droppedText(aString, name)

	events to interested Morphs at the mouse pointer.


	(e) keyboard events
	-------------------
	The World dispatches the following key events to its active
	keyboardReceiver:

		keypress
		keydown
        keyup

	Currently the only morph which acts as keyboard receiver is
	CursorMorph, the basic text editing widget. If you wish to add
	keyboard support to your morph you need to add event handling
	methods for

		processKeyPress(event)
		processKeyDown(event)
		processKeyUp(event)

	and activate them by assigning your morph to the World's

		keyboardReceiver

	property.
    
	Note that processKeyUp() is optional and doesn't have to be present
	if your morph doesn't require it.


	(f) resize event
	----------------
	The Window resize event is handled by the World and allows the
	World's extent to be adjusted so that it always completely fills
	the browser's visible page. You can turn off this default behavior
	by setting the World's

		useFillPage

	property to false.

	Alternatively you can also initialize the World with the
	useFillPage switch turned off from the beginning by passing the
	false value as second parameter to the World's constructor:

		world = new World(aCanvas, false);

	Use this when creating a web page with multiple Worlds.

	if "useFillPage" is turned on the World dispatches an

		reactToWorldResize(newBounds)

	events to all of its children (toplevel only), allowing each to
	adjust to the new World bounds by implementing a corresponding
	method, the passed argument being the World's new dimensions after
	completing the resize. By default, the "reactToWorldResize" Method
	does not exist.

	Example:

	Add the following method to your Morph to let it automatically
	fill the whole World, but leave a 10 pixel border uncovered:

		MyMorph.prototype.reactToWorldResize = function (rect) {
			this.changed();
			this.bounds = rect.insetBy(10);
			this.drawNew();
			this.changed();
		};


	(g) combined mouse-keyboard events
	----------------------------------
	Occasionally you'll want an object to react differently to a mouse
	click or to some other mouse event while the user holds down a key
	on the keyboard. Such "shift-click", "ctl-click", or "alt-click"
	events can be implemented by querying the World's

		currentKey

	property inside the function that reacts to the mouse event. This
	property stores the keyCode of the key that's currently pressed.
	Once the key is released by the user it reverts to null.



	(4) stepping
	------------
	Stepping is what makes Morphic "magical". Two properties control
	a morph's stepping behavior: the fps attribute and the step()
	method.

	By default the

		step()

	method does nothing. As you can see in the examples of BouncerMorph
	and MouseSensorMorph you can easily override this inherited method
	to suit your needs.

	By default the step() method is called once per display cycle.
	Depending on the number of actively stepping morphs and the
	complexity of your step() methods this can cause quite a strain on
	your CPU, and also result in your application behaving differently
	on slower computers than on fast ones.

	setting

		myMorph.fps

	to a number lower than the interval for the main loop lets you free
	system resources (albeit at the cost of a less responsive or slower
	behavior for this particular morph).


	(5) creating new kinds of morphs
	--------------------------------
	The real fun begins when you start to create new kinds of morphs
	with customized shapes. Imagine, e.g. jigsaw puzzle pieces or
	musical notes. For this you have to override the default

		drawNew()

	method.

	This method creates a new offscreen Canvas and stores it in
	the morph's

		image

	property.

	Use the following template for a start:

		MyMorph.prototype.drawNew = function() {
			var context;
			this.image = newCanvas(this.extent());
			context = this.image.getContext('2d');
			// use context to paint stuff here
		};

	If your new morph stores or references other morphs outside of the
	submorph tree in other properties, be sure to also override the
	default

		copyRecordingReferences()

	method accordingly if you want it to support duplication.


	(6) development and user modes
	------------------------------
	When working with Squeak on Scratch or BYOB among the features I
	like the best and use the most is inspecting what's going on in
	the World while it is up and running. That's what development mode
	is for (you could also call it debug mode). In essence development
	mode controls which context menu shows up. In user mode right
	clicking (or double finger tapping) a morph invokes its

		customContextMenu

	property, whereas in development mode only the general

		developersMenu()

	method is called and the resulting menu invoked. The developers'
	menu features Gui-Builder-wise functionality to directly inspect,
	take apart, reassamble and otherwise manipulate morphs and their
	contents.
    
	Instead of using the "customContextMenu" property you can also
	assign a more dynamic contextMenu by overriding the general
    
		userMenu()
    
	method with a customized menu constructor. The difference between
	the customContextMenu property and the userMenu() method is that
	the former is also present in development mode and overrides the
	developersMenu() result. For an example of how to use the
	customContextMenu property have a look at TextMorph's evaluation
	menu, which is used for the Inspector's evaluation pane.

	When in development mode you can inspect every Morph's properties
	with the inspector, including all of its methods. The inspector
	also lets you add, remove and rename properties, and even edit
	their values at runtime. Like in a Smalltalk environment the inspect
	features an evaluation pane into which you can type in arbitrary
	JavaScript code and evaluate it in the context of the inspectee.

	Use switching between user and development modes while you are
	developing an application and disable switching to development once
	you're done and deploying, because generally you don't want to
	confuse end-users with inspectors and meta-level stuff.


	(7) turtle graphics
	-------------------

	The basic Morphic kernel features a simple LOGO turtle constructor
	called

		PenMorph

	which you can use to draw onto its parent Morph. By default every
	Morph in the system (including the World) is able to act as turtle
	canvas and can display pen trails. Pen trails will be lost whenever
	the trails morph (the pen's parent) performs a "drawNew()"
	operation. If you want to create your own pen trails canvas, you
	may wish to modify its

		penTrails()

	property, so that it keeps a separate offscreen canvas for pen
	trails (and doesn't loose these on redraw).

	the following properties of PenMorph are relevant for turtle
	graphics:

		color		- a Color
		size		- line width of pen trails
		heading		- degrees
		isDown		- drawing state

	the following commands can be used to actually draw something:

		up()		- lift the pen up, further movements leave no trails
		down()		- set down, further movements leave trails
		clear()		- remove all trails from the current parent
		forward(n)	- move n steps in the current direction (heading)
		turn(n)		- turn right n degrees

	Turtle graphics can best be explored interactively by creating a
	new PenMorph object and by manipulating it with the inspector
	widget.

	NOTE: PenMorph has a special optimization for recursive operations
	called

		warp(function)

	You can significantly speed up recursive ops and increase the depth
	of recursion that's displayable by wrapping WARP around your
	recursive function call:

	example:

		myPen.warp(function () {
			myPen.tree(12, 120, 20);
		})

	will be much faster than just invoking the tree function, because it
	prevents the parent's parent from keeping track of every single line
	segment and instead redraws the outcome in a single pass.


	(8) damage list housekeeping
	----------------------------
	Morphic's progressive display update comes at the cost of having to
	cycle through a list of "broken rectangles" every display cycle. If
	this list gets very long working this damage list can lead to a
	seemingly dramatic slow-down of the Morphic system. Typically this
	occurs when updating the layout of complex Morphs with very many
	submorphs, e.g. when resizing an inspector window.
	
	An effective strategy to cope with this is to use the inherited
	
		trackChanges
		
	property of the Morph prototype for damage list housekeeping.

	The trackChanges property of the Morph prototype is a Boolean switch
	that determines whether the World's damage list ('broken' rectangles)
	tracks changes. By default the switch is always on. If set to false
	changes are not stored. This can be very useful for housekeeping of
	the damage list in situations where a large number of (sub-) morphs
	are changed more or less at once. Instead of keeping track of every
	single submorph's changes tremendous performance improvements can be
	achieved by setting the trackChanges flag to false before propagating
	the layout changes, setting it to true again and then storing the full
	bounds of the surrounding morph. An an example refer to the
    
		moveBy()
    
	method of HandMorph, and to the

		fixLayout()
		
	method of InspectorMorph, or the
	
		startLayout()
		endLayout()

	methods of SyntaxElementMorph in the Snap application.	
	

	(9) minifying morphic.js
	------------------------
	Coming from Smalltalk and being a Squeaker at heart I am a huge fan
	of browsing the code itself to make sense of it. Therefore I have
	included this documentation and (too little) inline comments so all
	you need to get going is this very file.

	Nowadays with live streaming HD video even on mobile phones 250 KB
	shouldn't be a big strain on bandwith, still minifying and even
	compressing morphic.js down do about 100 KB may sometimes improve
	performance in production use.

	Being an attorney-at-law myself you programmer folk keep harassing
	me with rabulistic nitpickings about free software licenses. I'm
	releasing morphic.js under an AGPL license. Therefore please make
	sure to adhere to that license in any minified or compressed version.


	VIII. acknowledgements
	----------------------
	The original Morphic was designed and written by Randy Smith and
	John Maloney for the SELF programming language, and later ported to
	Squeak (Smalltalk) by John Maloney and Dan Ingalls, who has also
	ported it to JavaScript (the Lively Kernel), once again setting
	a "Gold Standard" for self sustaining systems which morphic.js
	cannot and does not aspire to meet.

	This Morphic implementation for JavaScript is not a direct port of
	Squeak's Morphic, but still many individual functions have been
	ported almost literally from Squeak, sometimes even including their
	comments, e.g. the morph duplication mechanism fullCopy(). Squeak
	has been a treasure trove, and if morphic.js looks, feels and
	smells a lot like Squeak, I'll take it as a compliment.

	Evelyn Eastmond has inspired and encouraged me with her wonderful
	implementation of DesignBlocksJS. Thanks for sharing code, ideas
	and enthusiasm for programming.

	John Maloney has been my mentor and my source of inspiration for
	these Morphic experiments. Thanks for the critique, the suggestions
	and explanations for all things Morphic and for being my all time
	programming hero.

	I have originally written morphic.js in Florian Balmer's Notepad2
	editor for Windows and later switched to Apple's Dashcode. I've also
	come to depend on both Douglas Crockford's JSLint, Mozilla's Firebug
	and Google's Chrome to get it right.


	IX. contributors
	----------------------
	Joe Otto found and fixed many early bugs and taught me some tricks.
	Nathan Dinsmore contributed mouse wheel scrolling, cached
	background texture handling and countless bug fixes.
	Ian Reynolds contributed backspace key handling for Chrome.

	- Jens Mönig
